Guide to the Student Action With Farmworkers Records, 1950-2013 and undated, bulk 1992-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Student Action With Farmworkers records 1950-2013 and undated, bulk 1992-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Student Action With Farmworkers
128 linear feet Extent: 93,375 Items
Founded in 1992, Student Action with Farmworkers is a non-profit organization whose mission is to bring students and farmworkers together to learn about each other's lives, share resources and skills, improve conditions for farmworkers, and build diverse coalitions working for social change. SAF accomplishes its mission by working with farmworkers to address their concerns through documentation of human rights violations, grassroots education and mobilization, leadership development of young people, policy advocacy, and support of labor organizing. The Student Action with Farmworkers records include subject files containing correspondence, reports, articles, course material, internship applications, and other documentation of the organization's programs and mission, as well as posters used in protests and demonstrations. Major efforts represented in the collection include the Into the Fields Summer Internship and Leadership Development Program and Project Levante. Materials range in date from 1987-2013. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
RL.01128
Language: Material in English Spanish
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The Administrative Series and Student Projects Series are restricted. Researchers must receive prior authorization from SAF in order to access the material in these two series. All other series are unrestricted. For authorization please contact:
Joanna Welborn
Assistant Director
Student Action with Farmworkers
joanna.welborn@duke.edu
1317 W. Pettigrew St.
Durham, NC 27705
Phone (919) 660-3693
Fax (919) 681-7600
Once authorization has been granted, SAF will contact RBMSCL directly and provide name of researcher, dates of use, and which boxes may be accessed.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Student Action With Farmworkers Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2007, 2009, 2010, and 2013. Additional materials arrived from Joan Preiss in 2011.
Historical Note
[Adapted from Student Action with Farmworkers website: http://saf-unite.org/]
Founded in 1992, Student Action with Farmworkers is a 501(c)3 non-profit organization whose mission is to bring students and farmworkers together to learn about each other's lives, share resources and skills, improve conditions for farmworkers, and build diverse coalitions working for social change. SAF accomplishes its mission by working with farmworkers to address their concerns through documentation of human rights violations, grassroots education and mobilization, leadership development of young people, policy advocacy, and support of labor organizing.
Student Action with Farmworkers (SAF) traces its history to the 1970s when child psychiatrist Dr. Robert Coles and professor Bruce Payne led twelve Duke University students in a summer-long Migrant Project, investigating conditions in NC migrant camps, testifying before the Occupational Safety and Health Administration, and successfully lobbying for the creation of NC Farmworker Legal Services. In the early 1980s, Payne and other faculty and students at Duke founded the Interns in Conscience project of the Hart Leadership Program, and groups of students went to southern Florida during summer breaks to work with agencies serving farmworkers.
In 1990, a grant from the U.S. Department of Education to the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke funded college student volunteers documenting the lives of migrant farmworker children. Fourteen Duke students in the summer of 1990 and eleven more in 1991 participated in the Center's Migrant Summer Program along with several University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill students. In 1992, students from Duke and UNC participated in a joint service-learning class about farmworker issues and the summer internship program.
Inspired by other activists, a group of students enlisted farmworker advocates, farmworkers, and community members to incorporate SAF as a nonprofit in 1992. Since 1992, SAF has directly impacted thousands of farmworkers, students and community members
As of 2007, the goals of SAF include:
To provide farmworkers and their families with greater access to existing resources through collaborations with farmworker advocacy organizations and community groups
To link student groups working with farmworkers in order to share their experiences and ideas
To increase the involvement of farmworkers in leadership and decision-making roles within SAF and to encourage such involvement within other organizations working on farmworker issues
To create a supportive environment for the efforts of farmworkers to improve their status in our society
To create internships and other projects that are mutually beneficially for students and farmworkers
To encourage student commitment to justice and social action
To increase interaction, communication and understanding among people of different backgrounds
To provide students from farmworker families with educational and career opportunities
To provide information on farmworker issues for students, faculty, religious organizations, advocacy organizations, and community groups
Collection Overview
The Student Action with Farmworkers records include subject files containing correspondence, reports, articles, course material, internship applications, and other documentation of the organization's programs and mission, as well as posters used in protests and demonstrations. Major efforts represented in the collection include the Into the Fields Summer Internship and Leadership Development Program and Project Levante. Materials range in date from 1987-2013.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series: Administrative Files, Student Projects, Printed Material, Joan Preiss, and Oversize Material and Ephemera. The Administrative Files Series (24 boxes)contains organizational records created or compiled by SAF staff and are organized under the subseries of projects, fundraising, general administrative, organizations, and articles. The Student Projects Series (46 boxes) contains files related to SAF's student oriented projects including AIM Farmworker Class, Into the Fields and Levante. Material includes both project administrative files as well as student projects. The Printed Material Series (9 boxes), contains SAF's publications, SAF press coverage, and farmworker related print material. The Joan Preiss Series (5 boxes) contains records related to Joan Papert Preiss, an activist and long time collaborator of SAF. This series contains a variety of printed materials, primarily articles and newsletters, as well as correspondence, protest ephemera, promotional material for unions and activist organizations, meeting notes, etc. The series also contains student papers and photographs. The materials relate to migrants and farmworkers both in North Carolina and throughout the United States. Finally, the Oversize Material and Ephemera Series (9 boxes)contains oversize materials related to SAF's organized protests and boycotts and Levante activist theater group. Includes material from Burger King, Subway, Tomatoes, and Mt. Olive boycotts and protests. Also contains SAF publicity ephemera. Collection was acquired as part of the Duke Human Rights Archive. The Accession 2013-0079 Series contains administrative files regarding the operation of SAF, its collaborations with other programs and organizations, and its workstudy students and interns. This series also contains student documentary project materials, print publications of SAF and other organizations devoted to immigration and labor rights, audiovisual material, digital records, and ephemera.
Subject Headings
Agricultural laborers -- North Carolina; Agricultural laborers -- Health; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Children of migrant laborers; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Migrant agricultural laborers -- North Carolina; Migrant agricultural laborers -- Services for -- Study and teaching (Internship) -- United States; Migrant agricultural laborers -- Services for -- United States; Student Action with Farmworkers (Organization); Student movements -- North Carolina; Student service -- United States; Documentary sources for social change -- Agricultural laborers
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Files Series, 1992-2005, and undated, (24 Boxes)
  Access to this series is restricted to researchers who have received prior authorization from the donor. Please contact a reference archivist for further assistance.
  Contains administrative and subject files organized under the subseries of projects, fundraising, general administrative, organizations, and articles. Folders are organized alphabetically.
  - Projects Subseries
    Contains files related to various SAF projects and initiatives as well as other organizations' projects which SAF contributed to. These include Farmworker Awareness Week, Sowing Seeds of Change, Adelante, Farmworker Advocacy Network, and SAF fellowships. Materials include manuals, correspondence, budgets, goals, meeting and committee notes, research, and publicity material
    - Project files, Adelante (Box 8)
    - Project files A-C (Box 1)
    - Project files C-F (Box 2)
    - Project files F (Box 3)
    - Project files F-N (Box 4)
    - Project files N-S (Box 5)
    - Project files S-U (Box 6)
    - Project files U-W (Box 7)
  - Fundraising Files Subseries
    Contains files related to fundraising projects.
    - Fundraising files (Box 7)
  - General Administrative Files Subseries
    Contains files related to general office management.
    - Administrative files (Box 7)
  - Organizations Subseries
    Contains files related to organizations that SAF has worked with or followed, such as colleges and non-profit organizations. College files include information on fellowships and student activism and contain materials such as flyers, booklets, and correspondence. Other organization files contain publications, newsletters, reports, and correspondence from advocacy organizations, governmental organizations, etc. related to farmworkers, labor, and latinos nationally and in North Carolina
    - College files A-D (Box 7)
    - College files D-Y (Box 9)
    - Organization files A (Box 9)
    - Organization files A-D (Box 10)
    - Organization files D-F (Box 11)
    - Organization files F (Box 12)
    - Organization files G-M (Box 13)
    - Organization files M-N (Box 14)
    - Organization files N-P (Box 15)
    - Organization files P-S (Box 16)
    - Organization files T-Y (Box 17)
  - Articles Subseries
    Contains articles used in research and at conferences. General articles are organized in alphabetical order by subject. Includes articles on farmworker issues and activism.
    - Conference articles (Box 17)
    - General articles, agriculture (Box 17)
    - General articles, agriculture-farmworkers (Box 18)
    - General articles, farmworkers-health (Box 19)
    - General articles, health-organizing (Box 20)
    - General articles, organizing-racism (Box 21)
  - Photo Album Subseries
    Contains photo albums of various SAF related activities and staff.
    - Scrapbooks (Box 22)
    - Photo Albums, 1993-1998 and 1999-2003 (Box 23)
    - Migrant Educational Activities photo album, 1999 (Box 23)
    - Photos of youths by Julee (Box 94)
- Student Projects Series, 1986-2011, and undated, (46 boxes)
  Contains files related to SAF's student oriented projects including AIM Farmworker Class, Into the Fields and Levante. Material includes both project administrative files as well as student projects.
  - Duke Interns in Conscience and Migrant Summer Project Subseries,1986-1992
    This series contains files relating to one of SAF's earliest founding projects. In the early 1980s, Professor Bruce Payne and other faculty and students at Duke founded the Interns in Conscience project of the Hart Leadership Program.
    - Evaluations (Box 25)
    - Fundraising (Box 25)
    - House course (Box 25)
    - Housing (Box 25)
    - Internships (Box 25)
    - Sponsoring Agencies (Box 25)
    - Migrant Summer (Box 25)
  - Into The Fields: Administrative Subseries, 1993-2011, and undated, (22 boxes)
    Access to this material is restricted to researchers who have received prior permission from the donor. Consult Research Services for information on obtaining permission to access this material.
    Into the Fields is an internship program in which interns document issues and individuals in farmworker communities. This subseries includes administrative files related to interns and internship operations. General administrative folders are organized chronologically by year. Files on individuals and organizations are organized alphabetically.
    - General administrative files, 1993 (Box 26)
    - General administrative files, 1993-1994 (Box 27)
    - General administrative files, 1994 (Box 28)
    - General administrative files, 1994-1997 (Box 29)
    - General administrative files, 1997-1999 (Box 30)
    - General administrative files, 1999-2001 (Box 31)
    - General administrative files, 2001-2002 (Box 32)
    - General administrative files, 2002-2003 (Box 33)
    - General administrative files, 2003-2004 (Box 34)
    - General administrative files, 2004-2005 (Box 35)
    - General administrative files, 2005-2006 (Box 36)
    - General administrative files, 2007-2008 (Box 37)
    - General administrative files, 2008 (Box 38)
    - General administrative files, 2008-2010 (Box 39)
    - General administrative files, 2010-2011 and undated (Box 40)
    - Individual intern files, A (Box 40)
    - Individual intern files, A-G (Box 41)
    - Individual intern files, G-H (Box 42)
    - Individual intern files, J-R (Box 43)
    - Individual intern files, R-Z (Box 44)
    - Partner organizations, A-Z (Box 45)
    - Partner universities A-B (Box 45)
    - Partner universities, B-Z (Box 46)
    - Partner organizations, oversized (Box 47)
  - Into the Fields: Documentary Work Subseries 1991-2010, and undated, (6 boxes)
    Contains interns' documentary projects which may consist of interview transcripts, photos, and articles. Projects focus on migrant farmworker communities and individuals. Many focus on aspects of folklife and the day-to-day lives of individuals. Large projects taken up over multiple years include Recollections of Home and Folklife Documentary Project. Each year individual interns' projects are collected to form these larger series representing the works of all interns during each internship period. Projects are arranged chronologically by year. Audio, video, and digital material are located in the Audio/Visual and Digital Subseries.
    - W-9: Life's Learnings: Educations, 1991, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      By: Sarah Carroll.
    - Miscellaneous photos, 1991-2002, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - W-2: Oral and Written Comp. number 1, 1991-1994, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      Incomplete document, by: Sarah Carroll and Mike Evans, undated
      A Birthday for Emilia, by: Eric Jones, 1991 Nov. 24
      To all migrant farmworkers everywhere, by: LeeAnn Schrage, 1994
      How Much Do You Earn An Hour?, by: Reyna Nunez, 1994
      El Dia de Nuestra Salud/The Day of Our Health, A summary of the 1994 Hispanic Health Fair, by: Patience Harrison, 1994
      Untitled, by: Tammi Spruill, 1994
      Untitled, by: Veronica Hough, 1994
      Various poems and Some Thoughts on the Summer of 1994, by: Kathy Ray, 1994
      Untitled, by: Naomi Senzer
      From My Experience in Rockingham County, Little Willie, by: Montenique Nikkie L. Finney, 1994 July 27
      Don't Cry, by: Amy Glenn, 1994
      Untitled, by: Kate Graves, 1994
      Untitled, by: Martha Rodriguez, 1994 Aug. 4
      Journal Entry, by: Marla Randall, 1994 Aug. 2
      Little Guatemala, by: Gerardo Martinez, 1994 Aug. 5
      SAF Staff Orientation Rap, no author, 1994
      Creative abstract inspired summer 1994 internship, by: Tobie Bass, 1994
    - Staff scrapbook, 1995, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - P-3: Documentary Scrapbook III, 1995, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      Subject photos and staff photos.
    - W-7: Marla Goode's Summer, 1995, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - W-8: The Peaceable Classroom, 1995, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      By: Tara P. Knight.
    - W-2: Oral and Written Comp II, 1995-1997, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      Various poems by Alma Rojas, date: 1995
      Journal of an Outreach Worker, by: Palmar Plonk, date: 1995
      Untitled, by: Kiki Barnes, date: 1995
      Untitled, by: Juana Torres, 1995
      Mis Padres, by: Juana Torres, 1995
      Rescuing Gems from Caves and Flowers Deserts, Building Raging Fires from Smoldering Embers, by: Hugh H. Davis, 1995 Aug. 5
      Untitled, by: Cindi Lopez, 1995
      SAF Documentary Project, by: Myah Cook, 1995 Aug. 4
      A ?Better? Life, by: Lori White, 1996
      Untitled, by: Andrea Hickle, 1996 July 28
      Mi escuela es Mt. View, by: Edith Ledezma, 1996 May 16
      A History Lesson, by: Sarah Hennessey, 1996
      Sunflower Seeds, by: Tracy Thorpe, 1996
      Merry Christmas, by: Ramiro Arceo, 1996
      Una Entrevista con Felipe Dejuki Mendoza, no author, 1997
      Surveys administered by Lisa Stevenson, 1997
      The Inside Scoop on the Former Moxley Family Farmers, by: Jenny Sousk, 1997
      Opportunity of a Lifetime, by: Michelle Steiner, 1997
      Las Condiciones de los Trabajadores Agrícolas en Carolina del Norte, by: Hortencia Huerta, 1997
      Untitled, by: Rachel Avery, 1997
      Ese Varado, by: Marcella Hurtado Gomez, 1997 Aug. 5
    - W-11: A Teacher's Summer, 1996, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      By: Ben Edwards.
    - W-1: Field of Dreams...The Real Thing, 1997, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      By: Crystal Denise Hudson.
    - W-4: Maria Luisa Vela and Sharon, 1997, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      Title: Maria Luisa Vela, 19 Years Old, interviewed by: Kris Adams, 1997 July.
    - W-3 Work with 3 Students, 1997, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - W-6: Feeding the World's Children, 1997, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      By: Luis Mendoza.
    - W-5: Two Interns: Luis and Ethan, 1997, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      By: Ethan Leander Timm.
    - 1998 Theater Group, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - W-12: Living the American Dream, 1998, (1 of 2) (Box 48)
      Untitled photos by Donna Risteen
      The History of una Historia, by: Lynne Walter
      Photos and commentary titled: Celia and Studying Spanish, by: Janeth Serrano
      Economic Justice, by: Tony Macias
      Photograph taken by a farmworker (2), by: Ben Cook
      Settled Out but Not Settled Down, by: Andrea Robinson
      Various photos by Lane Gary
      Brenda Garcia - Tobacco Farmworker, by: Erica Lian
      Untitled photos by Delia Aguirre
      Clarence Ferguson - Telamon Corporation, by: Erica Lian
      Various photos by Candice Stringfield
      Tobacco Field Blues, by: Daniel Hill
      Various photos by Rosa Cruz
      It's a hard life, but a good life; by: Kendra Strauss
      A Classroom, by: Esteban Echeverría
    - W-12: Living the American Dream, 1998, (2 of 2) (Box 48)
      Untitled photo by Donna Risteen
      Documentary Project, by: Cindy Lopez
      Various photos by Alma Rodriguez
      Untitled poem by Michelle Otis
      Untitled photo by Esteban Echeverria
      Domestic Violence, by: Donna Risteen
      Las Hermanas, by: Alicia Doran
      Farmwork Irony at a Camp, by: Janeth Serrano
      Te Gusta Mi Casa?, by: Luis Maciel
      Untitled, by: Andy Smith
      Across the Nation, by: Irma Diaz
      Various photos by Shaundra Young
      Oral History of Sheila Payne, in her home in Durham NC, by: Melinda Steele, 1998 July 31
      FLOC Rally at Mt. Olive Park, speeches by: Virginia Nismith, Fernando Cuevas, James Andrews, Baldemar Velasquez, 1998 June 23
    - A Compilation of Documentary works, 1999-2000, (1 of 4) (Box 48)
      2000 Into the Fields Interviews
      Interviews with Lorena Ramirez by Danielle Davis, 1999
      Various photos by Wendy Sellers Campbell, 1999
      Aluminum Siding Warrior, by: Brady Rochford, 1999
      With Mom and Dad Quinceañera, by: Luis Velasco, 1999
      La Reina Del Pueblo, by: Laura McFarland, 1999
    - A Compilation of Documentary works, 1999-2000, (2 of 4) (Box 48)
      Interviews with Lorena Ramirez by Danielle Davis
    - A Compilation of Documentary works, 1999-2000, (3 of 4) (Box 48)
      Life on Easy Street, by: Rachel LaCour, 1999
      Untitled, by: Kate Rhodes, 1999
      Mango y Fresas, by: Angeline Echeverria, 1999
      Mi Forta/Mi Torta, by: Maria Garcia Campos, 1999
      Various photos by: Jennifer Sugg, 1999
    - A Compilation of Documentary works, 1999-2000, (4 of 4) (Box 48)
      The Piñata Summer, by: Ellen Szedon, 1999
      Jose Juan's Life History, by: Juan Carlos Vieyra, 1999
      Manuel Deciga's Life History, by: Juan Carlos Vieyra, 1999
      La Criatura Da la Bienvenida, by: Maria Garcia Campos, 1999
    - 1999 SAF interns loose slides, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - Educ 300 slides, 1999-2001, (2 folders) (Box 48)
    - Subject photo slides, 1999 and 2002; artwork slides, undated, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - Intern photos, Hannah Little and Gina Humble, 1999 and 2003, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - Southern Folklife box 2 slides, 2000, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - Subject photo slides, 2000-2002, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - Juxtaposition, by Angela Callanan, 2000 April, Farmworkers in NC, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - Folklife Documentary slides, 1999-2002, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
      Recollections of Home, subseries as follows:
      Section 1: Music and Dance Traditions, by: Alison Blaine, Jesse Gonzales, Ben Campos, Gerardo Martinez
      Section 2: Oral Traditions, by: Laura Greeson, Scott Pryor, Lorena Alvarez, Laxmi Haynes, William Norton
      Section 3: Artisans, by: Dulce Ibarra, Monica Smith, Susan Hicks, Jean Mathurin, Curran Geist, Andrea Waddle, Magdalena Villagran, Nkechi Ukwu, Coby Jansen
      Section 4: Culinary Traditions, by: Shana Jordon, Karla Rosenberg, Juana Ortiz, Alma Navarette, Raul de Anda, Hope Bastian
      Section 5: Religious and Ceremonial Traditions, by: E. Szedon, Brian Eichner, Marivel Gomez, Natasha McDonald, Erin Barker, Maria Ruelas, Bonnie DeBlois
    - CIW Action in FL, 2000, (1 of 1) (Box 48)
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, (1 of 7) (Box 48)
      In Their Own Words: Children's Interpretations of Folklife, by: Laura Greeson
      Salvador Tovar, by: Alison Blaine, 2000 Aug. 9
      The Hold Religion Has, by: Lee Abernathy, 2000 July 24
      El Grupo Folklorico del Catedral del Sagrado Corazón, by: Sarah Betson
      Versos, by: Benito Hernandes, 2000 July 25
      Maria Baltazar's Crocheting, by: Monica Smith and Dulce Ibarra, 2000 June 22
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, (2 of 7) (Box 48)
      Preface, by: Jim Hemming and Melinda Wiggins
      Interview - Baldemar Velasquez, by: Maria Alapisco
      The Folklorico Dance Group of the Cathedral of the Sacred Heart, by: Sarah Betson
      The Hold Religion Has, by: Lee Abernathy
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, (3 of 7) (Box 48)
      El Nuevo Sonido de Appalachia: Mariachi Tradition in the Western North Carolina Mountains, by: Alison Blaine
      I Love My Child, by: Ayesham Coleman
      In Their Own Words - Children's Interpretation of Folklife, by: Laura Greeson.
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, (4 of 7) (Box 48)